A Guide to the Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files, 1969-2001 (bulk 2000-2001)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files 1969-2001 (bulk 2000-2001)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/2.031
This collection consists of 25,000 items (47 Hollinger boxes, ca. 20 linear shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access is prohibited for ten years from the date of creation unless special permission is granted by the President's Office. Under the terms of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Sec. 2.1-343 (4), the records of the president or other chief executive officer of any state-supported institution of higher education are exempt from the law's access provisions.
Additional access restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Acquisition Information
These records were transferred from the Office of the President, Madison Hall, University of Virginia, through Jo Anne Birckhead, on July 10, 2003.
Scope and Content
These files constitute the major record series generated by the president of the University of Virginia, John Thomas Casteen, 25,000 items (47 Hollinger boxes, ca. 20 linear shelf feet) chiefly 2000-2001, but with some files going back to 1965.
The records consist chiefly of correspondence, but also include reports, minutes, clippings, memoranda, and related papers concerning all areas of business of the president's office. Major topics include Association of American Universities; athletics and the NCAA; the Council for Higher Education Accreditation; the General Assembly; gifts and grants; the governor of Virginia; the Mariners' Museum; the Medical Center and the Health Services Foundation; ROTC; and the Board of Visitors.
Arrangement
Both the series and file headings used by the president's office have been retained. Restricted material has been placed in its own series. There are four series: Series I) General Files (Boxes 1-39); Series II) Seldom Used Permanent Files (Boxes 39-42); Series III) Committee Files (Box 43); and Series IV) Restricted Files (Boxes 44-47).
Contents List
- Series I: General Files
  - Miscellaneous A-Al 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Am 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous An-Az 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - African-American Affairs - General 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Association - General and Board of Managers 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - American Association of State Colleges and Universities 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - American Council on Education - General 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - American Council on Education - The Presidency 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - Architecture - General 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - Art - General 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - Art - Arts, Planning, Development 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - Art - Bayly Museum 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Art and Sciences - General 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Associated Western University - General 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Association of Academic Health Centers - General 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Association of American Colleges and Universities - General 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Association of American Universities - General 2000-2001, (Folders 1-3 of 9 folders) (Box 3)
  - Association of American Universities - General 2000-2001, (Folders 4-8 of 9 folders) (Box 4)
  - Association of American Universities - General 2000-2001, (Folder 9 of 9 folders) (Box 5)
  - Association of Governing Board - General 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - Association of Governing Board - Advisory Council of Presidents 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - Association of Virginia Colleges 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - Astronomy - General 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - Athletics - Atlantic Coast Conference (ACC) 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - Athletics - General 2000-2001 (Box 6)
  - Athletics - NCAA 2000-2001, (Folders 1-4 of 5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Athletics - NCAA 2000-2001, (Folder 5 of 5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Auditor - Internal - General 2000-2001 (Box 7)
  - Auditor Public Accounts (State) - General 2000-2001 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Ba-Bm 2000-2001 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Bn-Br 2000-2001 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Bs-Bz 2000-2001 (Box 7)
  - Birdwood - General 2000-2001 (Box 7)
  - Business and Finance - General 2000-2001 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Ca-Cg 2000-2001 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Ch-Cn 2000-2001, (Folder 1 of 2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Ch-Cn 2000-2001, (Folder 2 of 2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Co-Cz 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - Career Service - General 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - Carr's Hill - General 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - Casteen, John T. III - General 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - Charlottesville, City of - General 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - Charlottesville, City of (PACC) 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - Chemistry - General 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - College Board - General 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - Commerce School -General 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - Community Relations 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - Controller (state) - General 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - Condolences A-Z 2000-2001 (Box 10)
  - Congress - General 2000-2001 (Box 10)
  - Continuing and Professional Studies - General 2000-2001 (Box 10)
  - Council for Higher Education Accreditation 2000-2001, (Folders 1-2 of 6 folders) (Box 10)
  - Council for Higher Education Accreditation 2000-2001, (Folders 3-6 of 6 folders) (Box 11)
  - Council for Presidents - General 2000-2001 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Da-De 2000-2001, (Folder 1 of 2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Da-De 2000-2001, (Folder 2 of 2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous Df-Dz 2000-2001 (Box 12)
  - Development - General 2000-2001 (Box 12)
  - Drama - General 2000-2001 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous E 2000-2001, (Folder 1 of 3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous 2000-2001, (Folders 2-3 of 3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Education School - General 2000-2001 (Box 13)
  - Engineering and Applied Science - General 2000-2001 (Box 13)
  - English - General 2000-2001 (Box 14)
  - Enrollment - General 2000-2001 (Box 14)
  - Environmental Sciences - General 2000-2001 (Box 14)
  - Equal Opportunity - General 2000-2001 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous - Fa-Fh 2000-2001 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Fi-Fz 2000-2001 (Box 14)
  - Facilities Management - General 2000-2001 (Box 14)
  - Faculty - General 2000-2001 (Box 15)
  - Financial Aid to Students Office - General 2000-2001 (Box 15)
  - Flowerdew Hundred - David Harrison 2000-2001 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous Ga-Gn 2000-2001 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous Go-Gz 2000-2001 (Box 15)
  - General Assembly - General 2000-2001, (Folders1-2 of 3 folders) (Box 15)
  - General Assembly - General 2000-2001, (Folder 3 of 3 folders) (Box 16)
  - General Assembly - Legislative Summaries 2000-2001 (Box 16)
  - General Council - General 2000-2001 (Box 16)
  - General Services (State) - General 2000-2001 (Box 16)
  - Gifts and Grants A-C 2000-2001, (Folders 1-4 of 5 folders) (Box 16)
  - Gifts and Grants A-C 2000-2001, (Folder 5 of 5 folders) (Box 17)
  - Gifts and Grants D-F 2000-2001 (Box 17)
  - Gifts and Grants G-K 2000-2001, (Folder 1 of 5 folders) (Box 17)
  - Gifts and Grants G-K 2000-2001, (Folders 2-5 of 5 folders) (Box 18)
  - Gifts and Grants L-P 2000-2001, (Folder 1 of 6 folders) (Box 18)
  - Gifts and Grants L-P 2000-2001, (Folders 2-6 of 6 folders) (Box 19)
  - Gifts and Grants Q-S 2000-2001 (Box 20)
  - Gifts and Grants T-Z 2000-2001, (Folders 1-2 of 4 folders) (Box 20)
  - Gifts and Grants T-Z 2000-2001, (Folders 3-4 of 4 folders) (Box 21)
  - Government and Foreign Affairs - General 2000-2001 (Box 21)
  - Government Relations - General 2000-2001 (Box 21)
  - Governor's Office - General 2000-2001 (Box 21)
  - Governor's Office - Administration 2000-2001 (Box 21)
  - Governor's Office - Commerce and Trade 2000-2001 (Box 21)
  - Governor's Office - Education 2000-2001 (Box 21)
  - Governor's Office - Natural Resources 2000-2001 (Box 21)
  - Governor - Technology - General 2000-2001 (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous -Ha-Hh 2000-2001 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous - Hi-Hz 2000-2001 (Box 22)
  - History - General 2000-2001 (Box 22)
  - Honor System/Committee - General 2000-2001 (Box 22)
  - Housing - General 2000-2001 (Box 22)
  - Human Resources - General 2000-2001 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous - I 2000-2001 (Box 23)
  - Information Technology (State) - General 2000-2001 (Box 23)
  - Information Technology (University of Virginia) - General 2000-2001 (Box 23)
  - Informational Assessment of Studies - General 2000-2001 (Box 23)
  - International Studies - General 2000-2001 (Box 23)
  - Invitations of Inaugurations 2000-2001, (Folders 1-2 of 3 folders) (Box 23)
  - Invitation of Inaugurations 2000-2001, (Folder 3 of 3 folders) (Box 24)
  - Invitation to Social Events 2000-2001 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous J 2000-2001 (Box 24)
  - Thomas Jefferson Foundation 2000-2001 (Box 24)
  - Joint Legislative Audit and Review 2000-2001 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous K 2000-2001, (Folders 1-2 of 3 folders) (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous K 2000-2001, (Folder 3 of 3 folders) (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous L 2000-2001 (Box 25)
  - Law - General 2000-2001 (Box 25)
  - Library - General 2000-2001 (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous Mc 2000-2001 (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous Ma-Me 2000-2001 (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous Mf-Mz 2000-2001 (Box 26)
  - Major Events Office - General 2000-2001 (Box 27)
  - Management and Budget - General 2000-2001 (Box 27)
  - Mariners' Museum 2000-2001, (Folders 1-5 of 7 folders) (Box 27)
  - Mariners' Museum 2000-2001, (Folders 6-7 of 7 folders) (Box 28)
  - Mathematics - General 2000-2001 (Box 28)
  - Medical Center - General 2000-2001 (Box 28)
  - Medical Center - Personnel 2000-2001 (Box 28)
  - Medical Center - Hospital - General 2000-2001 (Box 28)
  - Medical Center - Medical School 2000-2001 (Box 28)
  - Medical Center - Nursing School 2000-2001 (Box 28)
  - Music - General 2000-2001 (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous - N-Na 2000-2001 (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous - Nb-Nz 2000-2001 (Box 29)
  - National Association of State University and Land-Grant Colleges 2000-2001 (Box 29)
  - National Institute of Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism 2000-2001 (Box 29)
  - National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism Subcommittee on Student Drinking 2000-2001 (Box 29)
  - National Science Foundation - General 2000-2001 (Box 30)
  - Nellie May Foundation - General 2000-2001 (Box 30)
  - Newcomb Hall - General 2000-2001 (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous O 2000-2001 (Box 30)
  - Oak Ridge Associates Universities - General 2000-2001 (Box 30)
  - Omicron Delta Kappa - General 2000-2001 (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous Pa-Ph 2000-2001 (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous Pi-Pz 2000-2001 (Box 31)
  - University Parking and Transportation -General 2000-2001 (Box 31)
  - Physics - General 2000-2001 (Box 31)
  - Planning (Virginia 2020) - General 2000-2001 (Box 31)
  - Planning and Budget - General 2000-2001 (Box 31)
  - President's Senior Cabinet - General 2000-2001 (Box 31)
  - Procurement Services - General 2000-2001 (Box 31)
  - Provost - General 2000-2001 (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous Q 2000-2001 (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous Ra-Rh 2000-2001 (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous Ri-Rz 2000-2001 (Box 32)
  - Registrar - General 2000-2001 (Box 32)
  - Request for Nominations A-Z 2000-2001 (Box 32)
  - Research and Public Service - General 2000-2001 (Box 32)
  - Reserve Training Officer Corps (ROTC) - General 2000-2001 (Box 32)
  - Reserve Training Officer Corps (ROTC) - Air Force 2000-2001 (Box 32)
  - Reserve Training Officer Corps (ROTC) - Army 2000-2001 (Box 32)
  - Reserve Training Officer Corps (ROTC) - Navy 2000-2001 (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous Sa-Sh 2000-2001 (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous Si-Sn 2000-2001 (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous So 2000-2001 (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous Sp-Sz 2000-2001, (Folder 1 of 2 folders) (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous Sp-Sz 2000-2001, (Folder 2 of 2 folders) (Box 34)
  - Salaries - General 2000-2001 (Box 34)
  - Sallie Mae - General 2000-2001 (Box 34)
  - Senate (Faculty) (University) - General 2000-2001 (Box 34)
  - Sociology - General 2000-2001 (Box 34)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS) 2000-2001 (Box 34)
  - Southern Regional Educational Board - General 2000-2001 (Box 35)
  - Sponsored Programs - General 2000-2001 (Box 35)
  - State Council of Higher Education in Virginia (SCHEV) 2000-2001 (Box 35)
  - State Department of Education - General 2000-2001 (Box 35)
  - Student Affairs - Dean of Student Office - General 2000-2001 (Box 35)
  - Summer Session - General 2000-2001 (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous Ta-Te 2000-2001 (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous Tf-Tz 2000-2001 (Box 36)
  - Miscellaneous U 2000-2001 (Box 36)
  - United States Department of Education (USDOE) - General 2000-2001 (Box 36)
  - United Way/Combined Charitable Campaign 2000-2001 (Box 36)
  - Universities Research Association - General 2000-2001 (Box 36)
  - University Guide - General 2000-2001 (Box 36)
  - University of Virginia Investment Management Company (UVIMCO) 2000-2001 (Box 37)
  - University of Virginia's College at Wise - General 2000-2001 (Box 37)
  - University Police - General 2000-2001 (Box 37)
  - University Press of Virginia - General 2000-2001 (Box 37)
  - University Programs Council - General 2000-2001 (Box 37)
  - University Relations /News Office - General 2000-2001 (Box 37)
  - Miscellaneous V 2000-2001, (4 folders) (Box 38)
  - Virginia Business Higher Education Council - General 2000-2001, (2 folders) (Box 38)
  - Virginia Festival of American Film - General 2000-2001 (Box 39)
  - Virginia Quarterly Review - General 2000-2001 (Box 39)
  - Virginia Student Aid Foundation - General 2000-2001 (Box 39)
  - Miscellaneous Wa-Wh 2000-2001 (Box 39)
  - Miscellaneous Wi-Wz 2000-2001 (Box 39)
  - Miscellaneous X-Z 2000-2001 (Box 39)
- Series II: Seldom Used Permanent Files
  - Athletics - Aohu Bowl 2000 (Box 39)
  - Development - National Campaign Review Program II 1993-1994 (Box 40)
  - Development - National Development Council 1993 (Box 40)
  - Development - Post Capital Campaign 1985-1986 (Box 40)
  - Higher Education Act of 1965 1965 (Box 40)
  - Lawn Society Meeting 1965 (Box 40)
  - Medical Center - Health Services Foundation 1994-1998, (Folders 1-3 of 5 folders) (Box 40)
  - Medical Center - Health Services Foundation 1983-1994, (Folders 4-5 of 5 folders) (Box 41)
  - Policy on Non-Discrimination 1990-1991 (Box 41)
  - Visitors, Board of - General 1999-2000, (Folders 1-2 of 7 folders) (Box 41)
  - Visitors, Board of - General 1999-2000, (Folders 3-7 of 7 folders) (Box 42)
  - Visitors, Board of - Clark, Champ C. 1996-1999 (Box 42)
  - Visitors, Board of - Valentine, Henry L., III 1996-1999 (Box 42)
  - Visitors, Board of - Sasha Wilson (Student Members) 2001 (Box 42)
  - Weldon Cooper Center for Public Safety 2000-2001 (Box 42)
- Series III: Committee Files
  - University Committees - General 1968-1993 (Box 43)
  - Athletics Advisory Council 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Benefits Committee 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Commencement and Convocations - Subcommittee on Processions 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Commencement and Convocations - Subcommittee on Public Occasions 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action Committee 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Financial Aid Committee 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Information Technology Committee 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Libraries Committee 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Master Planning Council 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Names Committee 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Radiation Safety Committee 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Thomas Jefferson Award Committee 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Undergraduate Admissions Committee 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - University Press Virginia Advisory Board 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Virginia Quarterly Review Board 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Virginia Status of University Students Committee 2000-2001 (Box 43)
  - Woman's Leadership Council 2000-2001 (Box 43)
- Series IV: Restricted Files
  - Admissions - General 2000-2001, (4 folders) (Box 44)
    Restricted
  - Admissions - Law 2000-2001 (Box 44)
  - Admissions - Medical 2000-2001 (Box 44)
  - Applications of Positions 2000-2001, (Folder 1 of 2 folders) (Box 44)
  - Applications of Positions 2000-2001, (Folder 2 of 2 folders) (Box 45)
  - Arts and Sciences - Search of Dean 2000-2001, (2 folders) (Box 45)
  - Athletics - Director Search (2 folders) 2000-2001 (Box 45)
  - Business and Finance - Search for Vice President of Finance 2000-2001 (Box 46)
  - Darden School - General 2000-2001 (Box 46)
  - General Council - Search 1994-1996 (Box 46)
  - Jefferson Scholars Program General 2000-2001 (Box 46)
  - Law - Search for Dean 2000-2001 (Box 46)
  - Psychology - General 2000-2001 (Box 46)
  - Recommendations 2000-2001 (Box 46)
  - Student Affairs - General 2000-2001 (Box 46)
  - Student affairs - Fraternities/Sororities 2000-2001 (Box 46)
  - Student Council - General 2000-2001 (Box 47)
  - University of Virginia's College at Wise - Chancellor Search 2000 (Box 47)
  - Vice President and Chief Information Offices - Search (3 folders) 1999-2001 (Box 47)